Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is י"ד, yud-daled, and
we pick up at the very top and we spent yesterday figuring
out how the כהן גדול kohen gadol could use his backup wife
according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda so that he's always married to
exactly one and only one and only one wife at a one
and only one wife at the right time. Because the גמרא gemara
understands, makes it difficult in two ways. It understands that the word
ביתו beto means קידושין kiddushin is not enough, you need נישואין. nissuim.
If it was just קידושין kiddushin then you could have just stipulated
that the קידושין kiddushin kicks in for the second wife at the
moment that the first wife dies, it would have been easy. But
if it's נישואין, nissuim, it's not about just a, it's about an
actual reality of having begun to live together. So you can't stipulate
that when that, that that'll take effect, that's an actual lived reality.
So the גמרא gemara has to decide, has to sort of move
to the idea that you did the נישואין nissuim and now you
don't and now it's about making a גט get take effect as
opposed to making the marriage take effect, which makes it much more
complicated. And then the other thing that the גמרא gemara sort of
asserted that made its life complicated was that it can only be
one wife and not two wives. At the end of the discussion,
the גמרא gemara challenged both of those because by יבום yibum it
uses the word בית bayis and we say it even applies with
two wives and it even applies only after אירוסין erusin even before
נישואין. nissuim. Both of those assumptions were challenged based on יבום, yibum,
but the גמרא gemara somehow said יבום yibum was different, it kept
by its, it kept to its guns, and therefore it had to
make a very complicated type of a condition that he has two
wives, both of which he's נשואתיה nisuata to, they're נשואתיה nisuata to
him and he gives each of them a גט get on different
conditions and that way it'll work out that he'll only be married
to one wife at one time regardless of what happens.
The Talmud invented a way to have a non-married עגון. agun.
Okay, that's a good
question.
What? Second row was a girl.
The second row was a girl. Okay, all right, so now the
גמרא gemara is moving on to a new question. It's building up,
it's building up to a new question, which is if his wife
dies won't he be an אונן? onen? Now the הלכה halacha is
that a כהן גדול kohen gadol can bring קרבנות korbanot as an
אונן, onen, not a כהן הדיוט. kohen hedyot. It says ומן המקדש
לא יצא ולא יחלל את מקדש אלהיו, u-min ha-mikdash lo yetze v'lo
yechalel et mikdash elohav, that he doesn't leave the בית המקדש beis
ha-mikdash if a father, mother, or immediate relative dies. So he's allowed
to continue to do the עבודה avodah as an אונן. onen. The
הלכה halacha is he can't eat as an אונן onen the קרבנות,
korbanot, but okay anyway nobody's eating on יום כיפור Yom Kippur so
there shouldn't be a problem. I should also mention parenthetically
that the assumption here that when his wife dies he's an אונן,
onen, the פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim is that a כהן
גדול kohen gadol is not מטמא metame to his wife. The פשט
pshat of the פסוקים psukim speaks about everybody he's מטמא metame to,
לאביו ולאמו לאחיו ולאחותו, le-aviv u-le-imo, le-achiv u-le-achoto, etc., that's the כהן
גדול, kohen gadol, but anyway for a כהן הדיוט kohen hedyot when
it says who he is מטמא metame to, but then it says
לא יטמא בעל בעמיו להחלו, lo yitama ba'al be-amav le-hachalo, a husband,
a בעל ba'al cannot be מטמא metame להחלו le-hachalo to desecrate or
to violate. The simple sense is the תורה torah never mentions that
a כהן הדיוט kohen hedyot is מטמא metame to his wife and
therefore presumably he wouldn't be an אונן onen to his wife. However,
חז"ל chazal understand that actually based on the פסוק כי אם לשארו
הקרוב אליו, pasuk ki im le-she'ero ha-karov elav, his flesh that it's
close to him, שארו זו אשתו, she'ero zo ishto, they understand that
actually a כהן הדיוט kohen hedyot is מטמא metame to his wife
and is an אונן onen to his wife. רמב"ם rambam actually understands
that that's Rabbinic, interestingly, and even the Rabbis thought that institution was
so serious about it that they made it override the טומאה tumah
of the כהונה. kehuna. So anyway I did want to point that
out because here so a כהן הדיוט kohen hedyot is מטמא, metame,
a כהן גדול kohen gadol is not מטמא, metame, he stays in
the בית המקדש, beis ha-mikdash, but both of it is the assumption
though that it applies not only to the immediate blood relatives, you
know children, siblings, and parents, but also to wife and that therefore
and that a כהן גדול kohen gadol or הדיוט hedyot or a
normal person is an אונן onen when man is an אונן onen
when his wife dies. So the גמרא gemara is leading up therefore
to that question, to that issue, that he will, once his wife
dies, he will be an אונן. onen. Now again, why is it
a problem? He can do the עבודה avodah as an אונן. onen.
Well, because we had a statement that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said
כל היום. kol hayom. When we had a first statement that said
that a כהן גדול kohen gadol does the עבודה avodah as an
אונן onen but doesn't eat, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says כל היום.
kol hayom. What does כל היום kol hayom mean? And the גמרא
gemara says כל היום kol hayom means that actually although biblically he
does the עבודה, avodah, rabbinically we won't let him do the עבודה
avodah the entire day because we're afraid he'll come to eat from
the קרבנות korbanot and you can't, and as we said, he can't
eat from the קרבנות. korbanot. But that only applies that day, that
night already he's biblically not an אונן, onen, so we'll let him
do the עבודה avodah because even if he eats from the קרבנות
korbanot it would not be a problem. So let's pick up with
that on the top of י"ד עמוד א'. yud-daled amud aleph.
לומר, lomar, this is to tell you, שאינו עובד כל היום, she-eino
oved kol hayom, that according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda the כהן
גדול kohen gadol cannot do the עבודה avodah who is an אונן,
onen, cannot do the עבודה avodah the day that his wife dies
or an immediate relative dies. גזירה שמא יאכל, gezeira shema yochal, we're
afraid that if you let him do the עבודה avodah he'll come
to eat from the קרבנות korbanot and that he's not allowed, which
is quite fascinating that well we're going to get to that, which
is quite fascinating because that overrides, you know, the explicit biblical פסוק,
pasuk, you know, מן המקדש... min ha-mikdash... לא יצא. lo yeitzei. So
אמר ליה רב אדא בר אהבה לרבא, amar lei Rav Adda bar
Ahava le-Rava, so רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Adda bar Ahava said
to רבא, Rava, מי גזר רבי יהודה שמא יאכל? mi gazar Rebbe
Yehuda shema yochal? Is רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda really not allow a
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol to do the עבודה, avodah, to serve in
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash when he's an אונן onen because we're
afraid he'll come to eat? דתנן, detnan, we have our רבי יהודה
Rebbe Yehuda of our משנה, mishnah, רבי יהודה אומר, Rebbe Yehuda omer,
אף אשה אחרת מתקינים לו
שמא תמות אשתו,
af isha acheret
matkinim lo shema tamut ishto, you set aside a backup wife
lest his wife die. So that sounds like if his wife will
die we're all covered. But one minute, ואם מתה אשתו עביד עבודה,
ve-im meta ishto avid avodah, and if I'm sorry,
and if his wife dies his backup wife kicks in and he
continues to do the עבודה, avodah, ולא גזר רבי יהודה שמא יאכל,
ve-lo gazar Rebbe Yehuda shema yochal, and we're not afraid that if
we let him do the עבודה avodah as an אונן onen he'll
come to eat. Now there's an obvious answer here which Michael already
got a guess. אמר ליה הכי השתא, amar lei hachi hashta, said
back what type of question is that? התם, hatam, over there, by
meaning in our case, כיון דיום כיפורים הוא, keivan de-Yom Kippurim hu,
it's Yom Kippur, דכולי עלמא לא אכלי, de-kulei alma lo achli, nobody
eats. הוא נמי לא אתי למיכל, hu nami lo ati le-meichal,
he won't eat. You know, it's Yom Kippur, everybody knows you don't
eat today. You don't eat normal things, you don't eat קרבנות. korbanot.
Nobody's afraid that you'll come to accidentally forget and eat. הכא, hacha,
here, by a normal case of a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol doing
the עבודה avodah when he's an אונן, onen, דכולי עלמא אכלי, de-kulei
alma achli, that everybody eats. והוא נמי אתי למיכל, ve-hu nami ati
le-meichal, he's also going to come to eat. So just because he
makes a גזירה gezeirah during the rest of the year, he's not
going to make a גזירה gezeirah on Yom Kippur. Now the גמרא
Gemara then asks the next question which I was expecting someone to
ask. The גמרא Gemara says הכי השתא מידי דאנינות לאו חלה עליה,
hachi hashta midi de-aninut lav chala alei, what type of question was
it to begin with? Since when is he an אונן? onen? You
just got through saying yesterday that if his wife dies, he had
all these גטין gittin on condition and what would have happened was
if his wife died in the middle of the day, she would
retroactively have been divorced from him and he would only have been
married to his second wife. So he won't be an אונן. onen.
If his wife dies retroactively, he was divorced from her.
והא מיגרשה, ve-ha migarsha, he's divorced from her. So what type of
question was that?
So the גמרא Gemara says מיהא דאנינות לאו חלה עליה טרדא דלביה
מי לא מטרד. mi-ha de-aninut lav chala alei tirda de-libeih mi la
mitrad.
True, technically he won't be an אונן, onen, but he'll be very
distracted that his wife died. But so what? I mean just because
רבי יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda, just because רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda is concerned
about letting him do the עבודה avodah as an אונן onen he'll
come to eat, it's not exactly clear why that should have translated
into a similar concern of doing the עבודה avodah even if he's
distracted. So it's not at all clear how what this answer is
which really just goes to point out that presumably this question about
him being an אונן onen might have not bought into the whole
סוגיא sugya yesterday about all of these fancy גטין gittin and stipulation
and retroactive and might have assumed other ways in which the backup
wife can work. But anyway the גמרא Gemara here sort of bracketed
the fact that retroactively she wouldn't be the wife to ask this
question of אנינות. aninut.
Okay now we go on to the next משנה. mishnah. We actually
are now done with that first משנה mishnah about separating him out
for seven days and the backups, the backup כהן, kohen, the backup
wife. And now we go to the actual beginning of the seven
days being in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and what he would
do during that time. So let's take a look. כל
שבעת הימים, kol shivat hayamim, the entire seven days that he's in
the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, משנה, mishnah, הוא זורק את הדם, hu
zorek et hadam, so he's going to start practicing doing the עבודה.
avodah. You know, not just, not the עבודה avodah of Yom Kippur,
you can't do the עבודה avodah of Yom Kippur, it's not the
right time, but the regular עבודה, avodah, get used to doing it.
Especially if this was a bought office, he might not generally be
used to doing the עבודה, avodah, so he's going to start using
this time to practice. Also let's not forget that this is one
of the models for this is the מילואים. miluim. And the whole
idea of the מילואים miluim was the first initiation of the כהנים
kohanim into their service in the משכן mishkan and that they would
do, you know, be, use this time basically as practice, as orienting
and initiating into the service.
But you said you can't, can he still do like let's say
like the קטורת ketoret עבודה, avodah, we're not by the...
Here we go, let's take a look. כל שבעת הימים הוא זורק
את הדם. kol shivat hayamim hu zorek et hadam. So all seven
days he does the זריקת הדם zerikat hadam for the תמיד. tamid.
ומקטיר את הקטורת, u-maktir et haktoret, he brings the קטורת. ketoret. There'd
be קטורת ketoret that would be brought half in the morning and
half in the afternoon. So he would do that as well, which
all of this is stuff that he's going to be doing in
a different context on Yom Kippur. He's going to be doing זריקת
הדם, zerikat hadam, he's going to be doing קטורת ketoret although in
the קדש הקדשים Kodesh HaKodashim and not on the מזבח mizbeiach and
not on the מזבח החיצון, mizbeiach hachitzon, but nevertheless all of these
are relevant. ומטיב את הנרות. u-meitiv et haneirot. Now he also cleans
out the wicks and the lamps, you know, from the מנורה menorah
in the morning because you clean it out in the morning and
you light it in the evening. Now that by the way is
not something that's special to the עבודה avodah of Yom Kippur. So
it's interesting to note that he's actually just getting, doing all, just
getting into the mode of doing the עבודה avodah in the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash even if the specific things he's doing are not
directly relevant to what he'll be doing on Yom Kippur.
Is that something the כהן גדול... Kohen Gadol...
No, normally it would just be anyone. All this would normally be
done by normal כהנים kohanim because because during these seven days he's,
it could be that he's has very little practice doing anything in
the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. It was a bought office, you know,
for the last hundred years or so. So it could be that
we just want to get him used to what it means to
do the עבודה avodah in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. You know,
it's a, it's a seven-day
bootcamp. No, but on Yom Kippur he doesn't do the מטיב את
הנרות. meitiv et haneirot. No. Well... No, well actually we'll discuss. That's
going to be a debate whether all the עבודות, avodas, even the
non-special יום כיפור Yom Kippur עבודות avodas are done by the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol or not. But not necessarily. Okay, but, but yes,
these are things that first of all are the, like the נרות
neiros are not necessarily done by him on יום כיפור Yom Kippur
and certainly these things are not done by him during the rest
of the year. But this is essentially like a one-week...
Cleaning woman job?
Well, we can talk about that. I mean the גמרא Gemara goes
out of its way to say... I mean there's a special עבודה,
avodah, the whole גמרא Gemara says, you know, about the whole thing
about the תרומת הדשן, Terumas HaDeshen, you know, that even though it's
taking away the ashes, it's part of what it means to do
the עבודה avodah in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and not to
sort of, you know, denigrate that type, that aspect of the עבודה.
avodah. But the גמרא Gemara is certainly not... there's no hint at
all... if anything more it goes out of its way to point
to, to say that that has a very significant status. So there's
no sense here that this is a... not a significant עבודה. avodah.
But it's one of the major... one of the multiple עבודות avodos
that normally would be done by a normal כהן. kohen. So yes,
this basically is a week of full immersion into the עבודה avodah
of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. It's like a week bootcamp, you
know, to get him ready. And again, thinking about some model of
the מילואים. Miluim.
There's also talking about like the real difficult part where he has
to hold the כף kaf and the מחתה. machtah. Yeah, how do
they... I mean, that's tough butchering. I know.
So we'll talk about him, we'll talk about that. But that was
not what we're talking about here. Here we're talking about the daily
עבודות. avodos. Okay, not things that are specific to יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. Although some might be applicable. ומקריב את הראש והרגל. U'makriv es
rosh v'ha'regel. Now, what he would also do is he would put
the head and the first like leg of the animal, this is
again the תמיד tamid of the lamb, he would offer it up
because they would divide, cut it up into various portions and bring
the portions to the ramp, and then from the ramp they'd bring
them to the top of the altar. So he would... he's not
doing everything that goes on during the seven days, but key components.
Okay. זריקת הדם Zrikas hadam is of course the most important part
of the תמיד, tamid, that makes it legitimate, right? And he didn't
do the שחיטה? shechita? Right, he didn't do the שחיטה. shechita. And
he would be... and that could be even done בזר. be'zar. Anyway,
קטורת, ktoret, נרות, neiros, those are all like key things, different aspects
of the עבודה avodah and actually the burning of the first two
limbs, the head and the leg of the תמיד. tamid. ובשאר כל
הימים... U'v'shear kol hayamim... now, that's on those seven days. All the
rest of the days of the year, אם רצה להקריב מקריב. im
ratzah l'hakriv makriv. He doesn't do anything... he doesn't have any, you
know, it's not predetermined that what he's going to do. It could
be he does absolutely nothing. But if he shows up on any
given day, on Wednesday in the middle of תמוז Tammuz and says,
"Hi, I'm here, I'm the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, what do I
do today?", he can do whatever he wants. He's got the first
right to do whatever he wants. You know, what is it what
Mel Brooks said, right? "It's good to be king." It's good to
be כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. שכהן גדול מקריב חלק בראש ונוטל חלק
בראש. She'kohen gadol makriv chelek b'rosh v'notel chelek b'rosh. כהן גדול... Kohen
Gadol... what...
except when he died on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, like if he
died, he died. That's true. Because כהן גדול Kohen Gadol gets the
first opportunity to bring whatever he wants to bring. He shows up
on any day, he gets a choice. He wants to do an
עבודה, avodah, he's entitled to do the עבודה. avodah. He gets the
right to do any עבודה avodah he wants. And ונוטל חלק בראש,
v'notel chelek b'rosh, when they're dividing up the meat of the קרבן,
korban, he is the... he has the right to get the first
portion. He always can jump to the head of the line.
I had this naive view that everything was like so clean and
pristine. These guys must have been walking around looking like butchers, full
of שמוץ.
shmutz. Yeah, basically. Yeah, I mean the גמרא Gemara does talk about
walking up to their ankles in blood and all of that.
Gotta be a big mess.
Exactly.
Okay, so I mean they have like a regular water going through
the floor of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash to clean things off,
but it was not pristine. All right, מאן תנא? Man tana? מאן
תנא? Man tana? Who is the author of our משנה? Mishnah? That
after... because obviously it's got a problem here that notes about. אמר
רב חסדא דלא כרבי עקיבא. Amar Rav Chisda d'lo k'Rabbi Akiva. It's
not like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. דרבי עקיבא אמר טהור שנפל
עליו הזאה טמא. D'Rabbi Akiva amar: Tahor she'nafal alav haza'ah, tamei. So
היכי עביד עבודה? heychei avid avodah? So remember, we had taught, not
again in the previous משנה, Mishnah, but in a ברייתא, Baraisa, we
had taught that during the entire seven days they would sprinkle on
him the ashes of the פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. Now, we have
an interesting teaching of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says that if you are טהור tahor and you have the ashes
of the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, the water with the ashes sprinkled
on you and you're טהור, tahor, it makes you טמא. tamei. Now
everybody might say, "Oh, of course, isn't that what we say about
a פרה אדומה? Parah Adumah? It makes טמא tamei people טהור tahor
and טהור tahor people טמא." tamei. So normally that is... the Torah
says like that the person who does the sprinkling becomes טמא tamei
or somebody who touches it becomes טמא. tamei. There's no hint in
the Torah that if you actually are a person that has it
sprinkled on you, that you would somehow reverse, that even if you
were טהור tahor you'd become טמא. tamei. The normal sense is if
you have it sprinkled on you, you're טמא tamei you become טהור.
tahor. If you're טהור tahor presumably you remain טהור. tahor. But רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says no, it does the exact reverse. If you're
טמא tamei you become טהור, tahor, if you're טהור tahor you become
טמא. tamei. So therefore it says, look, this... it's quite ironic. This
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol was sprinkling on him the ashes all seven
days, in case, you know, for this... various reasons we said. You
know, best reason is the מילואים Miluim because then at least it
makes sense, it's just a סתם stam ritual. But the other reason
is that we really want to make him טהור, tahor, but there's
a question of making sure we're doing it exactly the right day,
so we do it every single day. So the... but the result
of that would be ironic according to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. We're
trying to make him טהור tahor by sprinkling every day. The result
is that we would actually make him טמא tamei if he was
already טהור. tahor. Now that טומאה tumah would not be a seven-day
טומאה, tumah, it would be a one-day; he’d go to the מקווה
mikvah and be טהור tahor that night, but at least you would
be טמא tamei for that day. So the גמרא Gemara says, if
according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, how can he do the עבודה
avoda for all seven days? Maybe this day you were טהור, tahor,
the ashes were sprinkled on you that made you טמא tamei for
the rest of the day, so he basically can't do the עבודה
avoda the entire any single day because he's already he's been טמא
tamei through the ashes.
So he was still agreeing that he gets הזאה? haza'ah?
Right. The גמרא Gemara isn't suggesting that anybody disagrees with that. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this,
although we did see somebody disagree with it before I think. Anyway,
the גמרא Gemara says like this, דתניא, detanya, ויזה הטהור על הטמא,
veyizah hatahor al hatamei, you this pure person should sprinkle on the
טמא. tamei. על הטמא טהור, al hatamei tahor, if you sprinkle on
the טמא tamei person, you make him טהור. tahor. ועל הטהור, ve'al
hatahor, if you sprinkled on the טהור tahor person, טמא, tamei, you
made him טמא, tamei, דברי רבי עקיבא, divrei Rabbi Akiva, that's what
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says. וחכמים אומרים, vachachamim omrim, and the sages
say, אין הדברים הללו אמורים אלא בדבר המקבל טומאה. ein hadvarim halalu
amurim ela bidavar hamikabel tumah. No, no, no, no, no. The reason
it says על הטמא al hatamei is not to tell you that
to have the reverse effect if he's sprinkled on a טהור. tahor.
That only if you sprinkle on a טמא tamei does it work;
if you sprinkle on a טהור, tahor, it's the reverse. That's what
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says. They say the reason it says על
הטמא al hatamei is to tell you that it's only considered a
sprinkling when it's done on somebody that is fit to be or
some thing that is fit to become טמא. tamei. What does that
mean? So מאי היא, mai hi, what's the relevance of that teaching?
דתנן, detnan, like we taught in the משנה. mishnah. נתכוין להזות על
הבהמה
והזה על האדם. nitkaven lehazot al habeheimah vehizah al ha'adam. Let's say
somebody intended to sprinkle on an animal, which is not something, I
don't know because he was crazy, it was not something that could
become טמא, tamei, but in the end it actually went on a
person. So it's a question how exactly to read this. רש״י Rashi
reads it that the key here is what happened, not what the
intent was. So it actually went on a person, so if it
went on a person, that's considered a legitimate sprinkling. So therefore, אם
יש באזוב
ישנה, im yesh be'ezov yeshaneh, if there's anything left over in the
אזוב, ezov, any water left on the אזוב ezov because they would
sprinkle with an אזוב, ezov, you know, dunked into the water, then
that water is still legitimate and you can go and sprinkle again
on the person. Now, נתכוין להזות על אדם והזה על הבהמה, nitkaven
lehazot al adam vehizah al habeheimah, let's say the reverse happened: tries
to do it on a person and it sprinkled on an animal.
So again, according to רש״י, Rashi, what defines the act is not
what your intent was but what happened. It was sprinkled on an
animal. Oh, it was sprinkled on an animal, an animal is not
something that can become טמא. tamei. So that doesn't constitute an act
of sprinkling. So therefore you use the water of the פרה אדומה
parah adumah to do something that was not an act of sprinkling.
So in that case, that invalidates what's left over on the אזוב.
ezov.
ישנה ישנה yeshaneh yeshaneh here means like שני, sheni, do it?
שני, sheni, do it a second time.
Yes, because
it's doing like עבודה avoda with the water of the of the
of the פרה אדומה, parah adumah, which invalidates it. אם יש באזוב
לא ישנה, im yesh be'ezov lo yeshaneh, if there's anything left over
you can not do it a second time. So again, you could
have read this the opposite because what's not clear is are you
focusing on intent, are you focusing on what happened. But רש״י Rashi
focuses on what happened and says if what you did was an
act of sprinkling, then that's not problematic. That's what you do with
the water of פרה אדומה, parah adumah, you sprinkle. So anything left
can still be used. You can sprinkle imagine you just you dipped
it in and I'm sprinkling on one, two, three, four, five people.
Right? Just because I sprinkled on one, I can keep on sprinkling
on the others. But if the first thing I sprinkled on was
not a person, then what I've done here was not a legitimate
act of sprinkling, it invalidated the water and I cannot use what's
left on the אזוב.
ezov. But why does it invalidate the אזוב? ezov? The אזוב ezov
was being used.
No, no, no, there's some liquid left on the אזוב. ezov. That's
the point. אם יש. im yesh. No, it's all I was using
it in the act. It was all part of the act. It
was all on the act that I was doing with the אזוב,
ezov, some left the אזוב, ezov, some stayed on, but it was
all the act was being done to all of the water on
the אזוב ezov and therefore before
you use one even though there's just drops of water.
Exactly. Well, yeah, but they're all together at the same time and
you're all doing it. So therefore it's like עבודה avoda with that.
So that's what the Rabbis learn: על הטמא, al hatamei, it only
constitutes an act of sprinkling if it's done on somebody that can
somebody or some thing that can become טמא, tamei, even if presumably
that person is currently טהור, tahor, so he'd have to be able
to become טמא. tamei. If it's something like an animal that cannot
be טמא, tamei, then it is a different type of an act.
That's what they learn. But רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva learns, no, it
only is effective on a טמא tamei person. On a טהור tahor
person, it has the reverse effect. So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי
טעמא דרבי עקיבא, mai ta'ama deRabbi Akiva, what's reasoning of רבי עקיבא?
Rabbi Akiva? נכתוב רחמנא ויזה הטהור עליו, nichtov rachmana veyizah hatahor alav,
let it just say the Torah says a pure person should sprinkle
on him, obviously we're talking about a טמא tamei person, that was
the context. מאי על הטמא, mai al hatamei, why does it underscore
the טמא tamei person? שמע מינה על הטמא טהור, shma mina al
hatamei tahor, only if you sprinkle on the טמא tamei person do
you make him טהור. tahor. ועל הטהור טמא, ve'al hatahor tamei, but
it's the reverse if it happens on a טהור tahor person, you
would make him טמא. tamei. ורבנן, verabbanan, the Rabbis would say, האי
לדבר המקבל טומאה הוא דאתא, hai ledavar hamikabel tumah hu de'ata, again,
it seems a little redundant, we just said this. That word טמא
tamei is to tell you it only is considered an act of
sprinkling if it's done on things that can become טמא. tamei. Okay,
it doesn't matter if you're טמא tamei or טהור, tahor, if it's
a thing that can become טמא, tamei, it's an act of sprinkling.
אבל הכא, aval hacha, but regarding your argument that if it's sprinkled
on a טהור tahor person it would have the reverse effect, so
they say
קל וחומר הוא, kal vachomer hu, that's a קל וחומר. kal vachomer.
אם על הטמא טהור, im al hatamei tahor, if on the טמא
tamei A טמא tamei, *tamei* person
it makes טהור tahor. *tahor*. A טהור tahor *tahor* person טמא tamei
*tamei*? That's crazy! So let's see the meat then, they'd be fine,
right?
Since meat can become טמא tamei, *tamei*. Right. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
*Rabbi Akiva*, היינו דקאמר שלמה *hainu d'ka'amar Shlomo*,
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
*Rabbi Akiva* says, you know what, you're right, it is crazy. Fine,
but that's what we say about the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah *Parah
Adumah*. That's what שלמה *Shlomo* says, אמרתי אחכמה והיא רחוקה ממני *Amarti
echkama v'hi rechoka mimeni*. I thought I would be wise and it
was distant from me. I thought I could understand כל התורה כולה
*kol haTorah kullah* and then I realized that I can't understand פרה
אדומה Parah Adumah *Parah Adumah*. It has the exact reverse effect. Okay,
so רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* said, you're right, it is
crazy, but what can I tell you, that's what a פרה אדומה
Parah Adumah *Parah Adumah* is, it makes טהור tahor *tahor* people טמא
tamei? *tamei* and טמא tamei *tamei* people טהור tahor. *tahor*. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, דרבנן *d'Rabbanan*, ההוא—I'm sorry—ההוא למזה ולמזין עליו
טהור tahor. ונוגע בהן טמא tamei. *hahu l'mazeh u'l'mazin alav tahor v'nogea
bahen tamei*. So the Rabbis say, look, you're right, there is cases
where a person becomes טמא tamei, *tamei* by handling the ashes of
the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah. *Parah Adumah*, just not by being the
recipient. Okay, there it's our קל וחומר *kal vachomer*, we wouldn't go
so crazy, but there are cases where a טהור tahor. *tahor* person
becomes טמא tamei. *tamei* by handling the ashes. And what is that?
The person that does the sprinkling, מזה maze *mazeh*, and מזין עליו
*mazin alav*, the person upon whom the sprinkling takes place, those are
always טהור tahor. *tahor*. נוגע בהן *nogea bahen*, who becomes טמא tamei,
*tamei*? The person who touches the ashes, he is טמא tamei *tamei*.
But if you're the sprinkler or the sprinklee, then you are טהור
tahor *tahor* even if you started טהור tahor *tahor* you remain טהור
tahor. *tahor*. Okay, so that's the debate, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi
Akiva* makes this very extreme position that it actually always does the
reverse.
So the ההוא *hahu* is someone else, right? What? That's what they're
saying—רבנן Rabbanan. *Rabbanan*.
Yeah, that's what's ironic about it is that yes, if you do
touch it you become טמא tamei, *tamei*, but in the normal cases
you remain טהור *tahor*. So they're not going to make it as—they're
not going to make
it—they're going to try to limit the sort of paradox of פרה
אדומה *Parah Adumah*. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* is willing to
take it to an extreme, the Rabbis are trying to limit it.
And now we're going really see how the Rabbis do try to
limit it, because the simple sense of the verse is that the
sprinkler becomes טמא *tamei*. So on the one hand רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* took from a subtle hint in the פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* which, you know, could easily be read otherwise, to say that
it absolutely does the reverse to you. Even if you're טהור *tahor*
and you're sprinkled on it makes you טמא *tamei*. The Rabbis then
go in the opposite direction, they take the simple verse which actually
speaks about becoming טמא *tamei* and they limit it. And they actually
show, you know, they actually
say that it does not apply in the cases it sounds like
it applies. Let's take a look. Says
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, ומזה טהור *u'mazeh tahor*? Is it really true that
according to the Rabbis that the one who does the sprinkling is
טהור *tahor*? דכתיב deksiv: *dich'tiv*, the verse says, ומזה מי הנדה יכבס
בגדיו והנוגע במי הנדה יטמא עד הערב *u'mazeh mei haniddah yechabes bgadav
v'hanogea b'mei haniddah yitma ad ha'arev*. It says the one who sprinkles
has to cleanse his garments, which means he becomes טמא *tamei* and
his garments become טמא *tamei* and he goes into the מקוה mikvah,
*mikvah*, and it says the person who touches it becomes טמא *tamei*.
So the תורה Torah *Torah* is explicit that it's not only the
one who touches it who becomes טמא *tamei*, it's also the one
who does the sprinkling. So how did you eliminate that from the
פסוק pasuk, *pasuk*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, לא, מאי מזה?
נוגע *Lo, mai mazeh? Nogea*. No, when the תורה Torah *Torah* says
the one who sprinkles it doesn't literally mean the one who sprinkles,
it means the one who touches. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
דכתיב מזה ודכתיב נוגע *dich'tiv mazeh v'dich'tiv nogea*. You can't say that!
Besides Michael's point, why should I reinterpret it? But it says both!
It says ומזה מי הנדה יכבס בגדיו והנוגע במי הנדה יטמא עד
הערב *u'mazeh mei haniddah yechabes bgadav v'hanogea b'mei haniddah yitma ad ha'arev*.
It says both! So obviously they're different people. So clearly also the
sprinkler becomes טמא *tamei*. ועוד *V'od*, and not only that, it's clear
the פסוקים pesukim, *psukim* that they are different categories. מזה בעי כיבוס
*Mazeh ba'ei kibus*. The one who sprinkles, it says יכבס בגדיו *yechabes
bgadav*. Not only is he טמא *tamei*, his garments are טמא *tamei*.
בעי כיבוס בגדים *Ba'ei kibus bgadim*. He needs to cleanse his garments.
נוגע לא בעי כיבוס בגדים *Nogea lo ba'ei kibus bgadim*. If you
touch it just you're טמא *tamei*, not your garments. So clearly there
are distinct categories and clearly the מזה *mazeh* is טמא *tamei* even
more so than the נוגע *nogea*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
לא, אלא מאי מזה? נושא *Lo, ella mai mazeh? Nosei*. Fine. You
know what מזה *mazeh* means? It doesn't mean the guy who sprinkles
it, it means if you carried it. So again, דניכתוב רחמנא נושא
*d'nichtov Rachmana nosei*. So let the תורה *Torah* say somebody who carries
the waters of the פרה אדומה *Parah Adumah*. מאי טעמא כתיב מזה
*Mai ta'ama ktiv mazeh*? Why does it say the sprinkler if according
to you the sprinkler is not טמא *tamei*? So הא קמשמע לן
דבעינן שיעור shiur הזיה haza'ah. *ha k'mashma lan d'ba'inan shi'ur haza'ah*. To
tell you, yes, you're only טמא *tamei* not if you do the
act of sprinkling, then you get a pass. You're only טמא *tamei*
if you carry it without doing the act of sprinkling. So why
does it say מזה *mazeh*? Because only if you carry the quantity,
the minimum quantity that you need for doing the sprinkling. Now what
is that quantity? So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, הניחא למאן דאמר הזיה
צריכה שיעור shiur. *Haniha l'man d'amar haza'ah tzricha shi'ur*. That's fine if
you say there is a minimum of amount of water that has
to be sprinkled on a person. Then we could say it says
the word מזה *mazeh* to tell you you need to carry that
minimum amount. אלא למאן דאמר הזיה אין צריכה שיעור shiur *Ella l'man
d'amar haza'ah ein tzricha shi'ur*, but there's a position that says that
even if the tiniest amount of water hits you you're טהור *tahor*,
there's no minimum amount. מאי איכא למימר *Mai ika l'meimar*? So what
can you say? The water... The word מזה cannot mean the amount
that you need to do sprinkling because there's no minimum. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אפילו מאן
דאמר הזיה אין צריכה שיעור, afilu man d'amar hiza ein tzericha shiur,
even if you say that the sprinkling does not require a minimum
amount, הני מילי אגב דגברא. hani mili agava d'gavra. That's on the
back of the person, meaning that there's no minimum amount that has
to hit you. If you're the one receiving the sprinkling, even the
tiniest spray, the tiniest dot makes you טהור. Okay, there there's no
minimum. אבל במנה, aval bemane, in the vessel, I dip my hyssop
into the vessel that has the water and the ashes, that there
has to be a minimum amount of water in the vessel. It
is not a minimum that has to hit you, but to do
the ritual of it I have to start with a minimum amount
of water. אבל במנה צריכה שיעור, aval bemane tzericha shiur, it needs
a minimum. דתנן, d'tanan, we taught in the משנה, Mishna, כמה יהא
בהן ויהא כדי הזיה, kama yehe bahen veyehe kedei haza'ah, how much
is the minimum amount of water that's considered enough for doing the
sprinkling? כדי שיטבול ראשי גבעולים ויזה. kedei sheyitbol rashei givolim veyaze. Now,
this is not so much a minimum שיעור shiur in a formalistic
way, it's just practical. There has to be enough water that I
can dip the heads of the hyssop into it and be able
to sprinkle, right? If there's such little water that by the time
I dip the hyssop into it it all gets absorbed into the
hyssop and there's no sprinkling to take place, then obviously I can't
physically do it. So it's funny to call that a שיעור. שיעור
usually means the physical act you're able to do, but we're going
to make a formal requirement that you need to do X amount.
Okay, here it's actually describing
the שיעור in terms of what's got to make it physically possible.
I guess that you could say theoretically it could be such a
little amount that normally a normal person wouldn't be able to dip
and sprinkle, but I somehow managed by luck to do it, and
even so it's no good because it's not the normal minimum. But
anyway, the point is is that there's a minimum amount of water
you need in the vessel to do the act, even if there's
no minimum of how much has to touch you, the person receiving
it. So what the גמרא Gemara says is yes, the תורה says
that the person who sprinkles the ashes of the פרה אדומה is
טמא, but the rabbis, in the exact opposite of רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva who wants to push the paradox, the rabbis are trying to
limit the paradox. And the rabbis are saying, give me a break,
the guy actually making you טהור becomes טמא in the process? So
no, the guy who's doing the sprinkling, he's טהור the same way
you're טהור. Everybody involved immediately in the process is טהור. It doesn't
matter if you start טמא, you start
טהור. המזה והמזין עליו טהור. ha-maze veha-mazin alav tahor. What does the
תורה mean when it says המזה ha-maze is טמא? That means a
person who carries it and is not doing the process. And the
reason it uses the phrase מזה is to tell you that there
needs to be a minimum amount of the water enough to do
the הזיה. But the point of the rabbis is to say that
at least if you're directly involved in the process you remain טהור.
They're trying to limit the paradox whereas רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, is
really trying to amplify it.
That's at least what I'm saying. I don't know, I mean, you
know, I can only speculate on what's behind it, but it seems
interesting that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. is pushing the paradox and they
are taking a simple פסוק that says המזה ha-maze is טמא and
saying no, no, no, it doesn't mean המזה, ha-maze, it means הנושא.
ha-nosei. Okay? Two separate
people. Yes, המזה ha-maze is the guy sprinkling and then the other
guy who is having it sprinkled on him.
Right, and then הנושא ha-nosei is המזה. ha-maze.
No, no, no. No, הנושא ha-nosei just means you're the guy who's
doing the sprinkling and I'm carrying it to you and I'm saying
here, here it is. I've carried it. There's three people. If המזה
ha-maze also is הנושא, ha-nosei, and now that then, you know, now
he would also it would affect him. But if all he's doing
is the act of sprinkling, then even though he picks up the
thing and he carries it in his act of sprinkling as it
was, that does not make him טמא.
By this definition, in fact, you don't know that there's not enough
until he dips it in and gives a flick and nothing comes
out.
Well, that is true, that is true. Okay, so what we have
said now is is that we have gotten to an interesting discussion
about the פרה אדומה and the paradox of the פרה אדומה and
רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva. pushing it. By the way, it's interesting, you
know, רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva enjoyed paradoxes, you know. רבי עקיבא Rebbe
Akiva was like the one who, you know, he saw the fox
coming from הר הבית Har HaBayit and he laughed and this is
a סימן siman of the גאולה geulah and anyway. So רבי עקיבא
pushes the paradox of the פרה אדומה. Everybody, you know, טהור people
become טמא, the rabbis limit it. But according to רבי עקיבא,
how do you sprinkle on the כהן גדול? Kohen Gadol? Every day
he becomes טמא. If he was טהור he becomes טמא, he can't
do the עבודה. avodah. So it assumes you do sprinkle, then it
would just say he wouldn't do the עבודה. avodah. So the גמרא
Gemara says it must be המרחץ ha-merchatz not רבי עקיבא. אביי Abaye
אמר, אביי amar Abaye, says, אפילו תימא רבי עקיבא, afilu teima Rabbi
Akiva, המרחץ כבי רבי עקיבא, ha-merchatz kivei Rabbi Akiva, דעביד עבודה כולי
יומא, d'avid avoda kulei yoma, it's just an interest of scheduling. You
get him to do the עבודה avodah the entire day, ובפניא, u'fanya,
and in the evening, meaning at, you know, 5:50 p.m.
right before sunset, מזה עליה maze alei you sprinkle, וטביל ve-tavil he
goes to the מקוה, mikvah ועבד הערב שמש, ve-avid ha'erev shemesh, and
then it's nightfall. So
what's the problem? Sure, he'll be טמא until nightfall, so you arrange
the sprinkling ten minutes before sunset, you have him go to the
מקוה after, and then he's טהור. for a whole 10 minutes, end
of story. The ברייתא beraisa is just a scheduling issue. Okay, fine.
So it could work according to רבי עקיבא. It is interesting that
the גמרא Gemara did not suggest the possibility that actually you would
not do the sprinkling every single day. That seems to be, although
not in our משנה, mishna, that seems to be a consensus. I'm
trying to remember from the גמרא Gemara before,
one
minute.
Yeah, there was a debate whether it would only be 3 and
7, or whether it would be, yeah, there was a position that
it would only be on days 3 and 7.
So that could have worked better if it was only on days
3 and 7, then at least it would have that would have
partly eliminated the question. At least you would have had all the
other days to do the עבודה avodah without having to worry about
it. Okay, anyway, let's, so anyway, but that's that, okay? So point
number one is, we've already learned before that you do the הזאה
haza'ah every day, or though as I just mentioned, there is an
opinion days 3 and 7. And now you do the עבודה avodah
every day. And according to רבי עקיבא that might create a problem
of making you טמא, but the גמרא Gemara either says it's not
רבי עקיבא or you do the הזאה haza'ah at the end of
the day. Now we get on to the actual specifics of the
עבודה. avodah. So what did the משנה mishna say? It said you
did זריקת הדם, zerikas hadam, and then you did the הקטרה, haktarah,
you burnt the incense on the gold altar, not in the קודש
קדשים, Kodesh Kadashim, in the אולם, Ulam, in the היכל. Heichal. And
then you did the נרות, neiros, you cleaned out the נרות. neiros.
So let's take a look. ומקטיר קטורת ומטיב את הנרות. U'maktir ketores
umativ es haneiros. So the גמרא gemara says אלמא, alma, you see
from
this, קטורת ברישא והדר נרות, ketores breisha vehadar neiros, the order of
the morning עבודות avodos in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash is first
you do the incense and then you do the נרות. neiros. That's
pretty clear from the משנה. mishna. ורמינהו, U'reminhu, I'll ask you
from a ברייתא, beraisa, right? We like to do a couple of
נרות neiros and then you do the קטורת.
ketores. Yeah, yeah, we'll get to that. Okay, so we teach a
משנה mishna in תמיד Tamid the following. מי שזכה בדישון המזבח הפנימי
ומי שזכה במנורה ומי שזכה בקטורת. Mi shezacha bedishun hamizbeach hapnimi umi
shezacha bamenorah umi shezacha beketores. So meaning, what רש"י Rashi points out,
that what we're doing is we're quoting the first line of three
separate משניות. mishnayos. The משניות mishnayos in תמיד Tamid talk about the
sort of schedule of the day and the סדר עבודה seder avodah
of the day in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So the first
משנה mishna says the person who got the cleaning of the
מזבח, mizbeach, here's what he would
do, ABCD. Then, the guy who got the cleaning of the מזבח.
mizbeach. Then it says the inner מזבח, mizbeach, not the outer one.
מי שזכה במנורה, Mi shezacha bamenorah, the next guy then, the next
person got the cleaning of the מנורה menorah and the preparing of
the מנורה, menorah, here's what he would
do, ABCDEFG. Then מי שזכה בקטורת, mi shezacha beketores, the person who
got now the burning of the incense, here's what he would do,
ABCDEFG. So it basically tells you each person what each person would
do in the order in which they would do it. Okay, and
there it makes it very clear that the order of the עבודה
avodah is, first you clean the inner altar, that's the one of
the קטורת, ketores, not the outer one with the sacrifices, then you
prepare the מנורה, menorah, then you burn the קטורת. ketores. So you
see the מנורה menorah comes before the קטורת, ketores, the opposite of
our משנה. mishna. So אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, מאן תנא
תמיד, man tanna Tamid, who is the author of מסכת תמיד? Masechet
Tamid? רבי שמעון איש המצפה Rebbe Shimon Ish HaMitzpah הוא. hu. He's
רבי שמעון איש המצפה. Rebbe Shimon Ish HaMitzpah. Now that's some name
to pull out of your hat, but what we're going to see
is, is that we're going to see in a minute that we're
going to quote a משנה mishna that he has, he says something,
okay, and therefore we are assuming that he is the author of
מסכת תמיד. Masechet Tamid. So basically what we're saying is, is there
a contradiction between יומא Yoma and תמיד, Tamid, what the order was?
Fine, they're different authors to those מסכתות. masechtos. The author of מסכת
תמיד Masechet Tamid is this שמעון איש המצפה, Shimon Ish HaMitzpah, and
he thinks that the order is, first you do the מנורה menorah
and then the קטורת. ketores. The author of יומא Yoma thinks that
the order is opposite, first the קטורת ketores and then and then
the מנורה. menorah. Okay, so the גמרא gemara says והא איפכא שמיע
לן. veha ipcha shemia lan. One minute, one minute. רבי שמעון איש
המצפה Rebbe Shimon Ish HaMitzpah says the exact opposite. דתנן, Detnan, what
did we talk, we teach in a משנה mishna over there in
תמיד. Tamid.
בא לו, Ba lo, meaning not that רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon teaches
the opposite, but that he is the opposite of, he's not the
author of מסכת תמיד. Masechet Tamid. We, meaning when it says איפכא,
ipcha, it doesn't mean איפכא ipcha in terms of the order of
the עבודה, avodah, but it means that רבי שמעון איש המצפה Rebbe
Shimon Ish HaMitzpah is, it's the opposite of what you said, he's
not the author of מסכת תמיד, Masechet Tamid, he's a contrary voice
to מסכת תמיד. Masechet Tamid. How do you know that? דתנן, Detnan,
we taught in the משנה. mishna. בא לו לקרן מזרחית צפונית. Ba
lo lekeren mizrachis tzonis. It talks how you do the זריקת הדם
zerikas hadam by the קרבנות. korbanos. Okay, so basically the way you
would
do the זריקת הדם zerikas hadam
would be that you would do anything other than a חטאת, chatas,
you would do two which is four.
So meaning, here's your
ramp, here's your מזבח, mizbeach,
okay,
whatever, anyway. Okay, so this is the,
this is, here east north west. So you would go up here,
you would turn to your right, because you always turn to your
right, which is why like with a כלה kallah walking around the
חתן, chosson, you're always going counter-clockwise. Okay, so you turn to your
right and the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol walks around like that. Okay,
so he would do the sprinkling on two corners, which, and he'd
make them hit at, he'd make them hit an angle. He would
do the sprinkling, and so the blood, okay, so
here and then he'd walk around and then he would do it
at this angle. Okay, so he threw the blood there, not sprinkling,
throwing it, right? And he'd do two, which would manage to get
all four corners. So that's what the משנה Mishnah in תמיד Tamid
teaches. It says, בא לו לקרן מזרחית צפונית, Ba lo lekeren mizrachit
tzephonit, he went up the ramp, he came to the northeast corner,
right? בא לו לקרן מזרחית צפונית, Ba lo lekeren mizrachit tzephonit, נותן
מזרחית צפונה, Noten mizrachit tzephona,
he puts the blood, he throws the blood that it hits on
the east and the north. מערבית דרומית, Maaravit dromit, then he comes
to the southwest corner, okay? נותן מערבה דרומה, Noten maarava droma, he
puts the blood on the south and the west. ותניא לה, Ve-tanya
lah, that's what the משנה Mishnah says. Then a ברייתא Braita teaches,
רבי שמעון איש המצפה משנה בתמיד. Rabbi Shimon Ish HaMitzpah meshane ba-Tamid.
He says that would be the case by all קרבנות, korbanot, except
the חטאת chatat by the way. חטאת Chatat would be on the
placing of the blood on the actual horns on the corners. That
would be by all the קרבנות, korbanot, you're right. But by the
קרבן תמיד, korban Tamid, we're going to treat the קרבן תמיד korban
Tamid differently. And what do we do by the תמיד? Tamid? He
would משנה, meshane, he would treat differently the תמיד. Tamid. And what
does he do? מזרחית צפונית נותן מזרחית צפונה. Mizrachit tzephonit noten mizrachit
tzephona. I agree that northeast, he does one throw and it hits
the north and the east. But מערבית
דרומית, maaravit dromit, when he got to the southwest, so נותן מערבה,
noten maarava, there he does two applications, not one throw that hits
two corners, that hits two sides, but two separate applications. First he
does the west, ואחר כך נותן דרומה, ve-achar kach noten droma, then
he does the south.
So according to him, you stand at
this corner and you throw it and it hits these two, then
you get over here and you do two applications. First you throw
there and then you throw there. We'll get to this in תמיד.
Tamid. Okay, why he feels that it's different.
Is he walking around the base at the bottom?
No, he's actually walking around, what's that thing called?
He's actually walking around like the כרכוב. karkov. He's actually walking around
some like middle-level ramp, okay.
The thing that's
like a בליטה belitah that goes around. Exactly.
So anyway, the relevant for us is is that the, you have
the סתם משנה stam Mishnah in תמיד, Tamid, and then you have
a ברייתא Braita that this רבי שמעון איש המצפה Rabbi Shimon Ish
HaMitzpah has a contrary voice to the סתם משנה. stam Mishnah. So
it's nice that you're honed in on this, and on him, first
of all, there are very few named voices in תמיד Tamid anyway,
a lot of it is סתם. stam. So you honed in on
him as the author of תמיד, Tamid, but he's not the author
of תמיד, Tamid, he's the contrary voice to the author of תמיד.
Tamid. Okay, so he, you can't say that the משניות mishnayot of
תמיד Tamid are going according to him, clearly he argues on the
משניות mishnayot of תמיד. Tamid.
How does the rule of סתם משנה רבי מאיר stam Mishnah Rabbi
Meir play into all this?
Yeah, I could have said that, but we're trying to, yeah, it's
not clear why it doesn't go straight there. Clearly it has this
name, and it wants to, you know, sort of pin something on
this name. So the גמרא says, okay. אלא אמר רבי יוחנן, Ela
amar Rabbi Yochanan, so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said fine, מאן תנא
סדר יומא רבי שמעון איש המצפה הוא. man tana seder Yoma Rabbi
Shimon Ish HaMitzpah hu. Right? Fine, okay. So if רבי שמעון איש
המצפה Rabbi Shimon Ish HaMitzpah is the contrary voice in תמיד, Tamid,
then we'll say that he's the author here in יומא. Yoma. All
we got to do is just say that the author of יומא
Yoma is different than the author of תמיד. Tamid. So יומא, Yoma,
the order was קטורת ketoret and מנורה, menorah, תמיד Tamid it was
מנורה menorah and קטורת. ketoret. Fine, they argue. There's one author of
מסכת תמיד, masechet Tamid, there's one author of מסכת יומא, masechet Yoma,
so this רבי שמעון איש המצפה Rabbi Shimon Ish HaMitzpah who we
know argues on תמיד, Tamid, he'll be our author of יומא Yoma
and say the order is different. Okay, גמרא says don't think you're
going to get out of it so
easily. ורמי סדר יומא אסדר יומא, U-remi seder Yoma a-seder Yoma, I'll
show you a contradiction even within your משניות mishnayot of יומא Yoma
about which comes first, the קטורת ketoret or the מנורה. menorah. דתנן,
De-tenan, we taught in a later משנה, Mishnah, פייס שני, payis sheni,
because what we're about to shift into in our מסכת masechet is
before we get back talking about the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol on
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, we're going to sort of spend time talking
about what the normal עבודה avodah would look on a normal day
in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. And in that description of the
normal עבודה avodah of the normal day, it talks about four lotteries
that they had every morning. Basically they got all the כהנים kohanim
together, they had them all stand in a circle, they randomly picked
one, we'll see later how they picked one, and from that guy
it says okay you, you do, there are like ten עבודות avodot
to be done now starting from you, you do one, then two,
then three, then four, then five, then six, then seven, and those
ten guys do the next ten עבודות. avodot. Then they all go
do their עבודות, avodot, and a little while later after they're done,
they all get together, do another lottery, and randomly pick somebody to
do the next thing, you know, and then they, so they have
four separate lotteries and each lottery they might be picking one person,
they might be picking a series of people to do the next
number of עבודות. avodot. That's what would happen sort of as they
would be doing this, you know, one of the reasons is that
it would just create a lot of like busyness and commotion and
excitement in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and that was seen as
a way of heightening the sort of respect and, you know, the
importance of what was going on. Lotteries each lottery they might be
picking one person they might be picking a series of people to
do the next number of עבודות. avodahs. That's what happened sort of
as they would be doing this. One of the reasons is that
it would just create a lot of busyness and commotion and excitement
in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, and that was seen as a
way of heightening the sort of respect and the importance of what
was going on. So in that discussion of the various lotteries that
they would do, here's what it says. It says פייס השני, payis
hasheini, the second lottery, they gather everybody together and then one guy
would be picked at random and starting from him מי שוחט mi
shocheit who would do the שחיטה, shechitah, the first guy that they
picked would do the שחיטה shechitah and then going around the circle
מי זורק mi zoreik who would do the זריקה, zrikah, the next
guy would meaning it this lottery would determine who would do these
cause the first guy they picked would do the שחיטה shechitah and
then moving around the circle of the תמיד tamid of the daily
sacrifice and then moving around the circle מי זורק mi zoreik the
next who would do the זריקה zrikah and throwing the blood, מי
מדשן המזבח הפנימי mi medashein hamizbeiach hapnimi who would clean the inner
altar, מי מדשן המנורה mi medashein hamenorah who would clean the מנורה,
menorah, מי מעלה איברים לכבש mi ma’aleh evarim lakevesh who would be
the לכבש, lakevesh, excuse me I do that I got it wrong,
who would bring the limbs of the תמיד tamid up onto
midway? They would do the תמיד tamid in two stages. They dismember
it and bring all the limbs halfway to onto the ramp halfway
and then they'd have a later stage where they'd bring it from
the midpoint on the ramp to the top of the מזבח mizbeiach
and offer it off. Okay so who would bring them to the
ramp? That's what they would do in the second lottery.
There were heavy, it
would divide it up, they would divide it amongst many כהנים, kohanim,
we'll see. Okay so it wasn't one person right?
Did they use like wheelbarrows and things they carried?
They carried it. Okay that would be the second. פייס השלישי, payis
hashlishi, the third, חדשים לקטורת בואו והפיסו. chadashim laktoret bo’u vehapisu.
They said anybody who has never yet had a chance to do
the קטורת, ktoret, the incense, come and be part of the lottery.
This lottery would only be for people that had never done the
קטורת ktoret before because it was understood that the קטורת ktoret was
like a סגולה, segulah, if you did the קטורת ktoret you would
become rich and therefore we'll see okay and because of that they
didn't want anybody to have an opportunity to do it twice only
new people could do it. So anyway the point for us is
is that it's very clear what the order is. The order is
cleaning of the inner altar, מנורה menorah to קטורת, ktoret, right? Which
is what we say over there in תמיד, tamid, cleaning of the
inner altar, מנורה, menorah, קטורת. ktoret. But it's not what we say
here. Here we say קטורת ktoret and then מנורה. menorah. So we
have later in our מסכת masechet and in תמיד tamid that it
says that the מנורה menorah comes first. How do you deal with
our first משנה mishnah here that says the קטורת ktoret comes first?
So אמר amar, אביי, Abaye so says אביי, Abaye, לא קשיא, lo
kashya, it's not difficult. כאן בהטבת שתי נרות כאן בהטבת חמש נרות.
kan betivot shtei neirot kan betivot chamesh neirot. So it's what Michael
said which is that the גמרא is going to learn out later
that they would divide up the cleaning of the מנורה menorah into
two stages. Okay first they would clean out you know what do
you call it first they would do two and then they would
go ahead and they would do the קטורת ktoret and then they'd
come back and then they would do five. Okay wait a minute
no it's the opposite order. Okay which is why אביי Abaye said
the opposite order which is why I hesitated. First they would do
five then they would do the קטורת ktoret then they'd come back
and do the last two. Okay I know it's a little strange
the way he says it. Okay but when do we say in
our משנה mishnah that the נרות neirot comes later? That's the last
two. When do we say in all those other משניות mishnayot and
תמיד tamid and later that the נרות neirot comes first? That's the
first five. So you would do five, we'll see when we get
to it, you would do five then you would do קטורת ktoret
then you would do two so some of them say one comes
first some say the other comes first it's really that they came
both before and after. Okay so the גמרא says למימרא דבקטורת מפסיקו
להו? lemeimra d’baktoret mafsiku lehu? So that sounds like that what they
used because everybody assumes as we'll see as we continue that there
would be some act that would be done between the five and
the two of the נרות neirot but the question is which act?
So what you have to know is the following you have to
know that basically you have the following order was agreed upon. You
had the דם התמיד, dam hatamid, you had the דם התמיד, dam
hatamid, okay then you had the the מנורה menorah of doing five
then the מנורה menorah of doing two, I'm sorry. So you had
the מנורה menorah five and the מנורה menorah of doing two and
the quest and the other thing that we know by the way
is that first you do the דם התמיד dam hatamid and then
you do the קטורת ktoret that the קטורת ktoret comes after the
דם. dam. Okay so let's know that this is the order know
that this is broken up. So there's a debate how would you
break this up? There's two possibilities okay you could
do it the following you could do דם, dam, מנורה, menorah, קטורת,
ktoret, מנורה. menorah. That
sort of fits with what we've
been saying right because some of them say because
because because then you have because then certain things say sort of
you know like our משנה mishnah says you do the דם, dam,
what does our משנה mishnah say come I'm getting confused already קטורת
ונרות, ktoret v’neirot, קטורת ונרות. ktoret v’neirot. So our משנה mishnah says
do the דם, dam, קטורת ktoret and נרות neirot so that sort
of skips over this דם, dam, קטורת ktoret and נרות. neirot. But
other משניות mishnayot speak about the דם, dam, מנורה menorah or speak
about the מנורה menorah and the קטורת ktoret speak about this. Anyway
that's one possibility. But another possibility is okay so דם dam and
קטורת ktoret have to come in that order that's assumed so the
question is which breaks up the מנורה? menorah? Does the דם dam
break up the מנורה menorah or does the קטורת ktoret break up
the מנורה? menorah? So to explain our problem that some משנה... mishnah...
And some that say מנורה menorah and קטורת ketoret and some that
say קטורת ketoret and מנורה. menorah. Is there a reason for any
of these, you have פסוקים, right? Yeah. Well, we'll worry about why
what's based on it in a minute, but there's an assumption that
it has to be דם dam and קטורת, ketoret, and an assumption
that the מנורה menorah has to be broken up, and
the question is, how are they broken up? But did you assume
דם dam comes first? What? They're all assuming דם? dam? Well, yes,
until now, but we're about to challenge that, so let's take a
look. Okay, our משנה mishna mentioned the דם, dam, right? Our משנה
mishna says זורק את הדם. zorek es hadam. The other משניות mishnayos
spoke about מדשן את המנורה, medashen es hamenorah, מדשן את המזבח, medashen
es hamizbeach, did not mention דם. dam. Okay, but anyway, אביי's Abaye
answer, this was אביי's Abaye answer, right? That the קטורת ketoret came
in the middle and that explained some could say מנורה menorah and
קטורת ketoret and some say קטורת ketoret and מנורה. menorah. But now
let's see what the גמרא asks, because the גמרא says: למימרא דבקטורת
מפסיק להו? lemeimra d'biktoret mafsik lehu? You're, that's, you're saying that the
קטורת ketoret is what divided the two parts of the מנורה? menorah?
והא אביי מסדר מערכה משמיה דגמרא. veha Abaye mesader maaracha mishmeih degemara.
אביי Abaye was, it's a funny phrase, מסדר מערכה, mesader maaracha, because
literally that means like he would, he would like, you know, סידור
מערכה siddur maaracha is what you would do when you would sort
of place the wood on the wood fire on top of the
מזבח, mizbeach, is that you would like, you know, organize the, you
know, the, the pile. But here, מסדר מערכה, mesader maaracha, like comes
from the word of like, you know, to be מסדר mesader a
teaching of משניות. mishnayos. So he would teach over the order of
doing the עבודה avodah in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash in the
name of tradition. He had a tradition about the order of the
עבודה avodah in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. ובדם התמיד מפסיק להו.
uvedam hatamid mafsik lehu. And when he teaches over the order of
the עבודה avodah in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, he says it's
the blood that interrupts the two parts of the מנורה, menorah, not
the קטורת. ketoret. Okay, so how do you explain that? אמר ליה
לא קשיא הא דאבא שאול הא דרבנן. amar lei lo kashya ha
d'Abba Shaul ha deRabbanan. It's not a problem. Again, it's going according
to different opinions. One is going according to אבא שאול, Abba Shaul,
one is going according to רבנן. Rabbanan, What is this debate אבא
שאול Abba Shaul and the רבנן, which interrupts the
תמיד, tamid, which interrupts the מנורה, menorah, is it the קטורת ketoret
or is it the דם? dam? דתניא, detanya, we learned in a
ברייתא: braisa: לא ייטיב את הנרות ואחר כך יקטיר אלא יקטיר ואחר
כך ייטיב. lo yeitiv es haneros veachar kach yaktir ella yaktir veachar
kach yeitiv. Okay, do not go ahead and clean the מנורות menoros
and then do the הקטרה, haktara, rather do the הקטרה haktara and
afterwards clean the נרות. neros. Now what does that mean? So רש"י
Rashi explains what that means is do not do all seven of
the מנורות menoros and then do the הקטרה, haktara, אלא יקטיר. ella
yaktir.
Sorry, הקטרה haktara is, no,
הקטרה haktara is קטורת, ketoret, קטורת, ketoret, the incense. Rather do the
incense and then finish. Okay, meaning that the way that's being read
is don't do, meaning, don't do all of the מנורה menorah and
then do the קטורת. ketoret. No, do the incense in between and
then finish up. Okay, it's a little vague because it sounds like
it doesn't need to interrupt, but that's how it's being read. Okay,
so first do the קטורת ketoret and then finish up the מנורה.
menorah. So that's being read the way we were reading the משניות
mishnayos before with the קטורת ketoret interrupting the מנורה. menorah. That's תנא
קמא.
Tanna Kamma.
Okay, let's worry about the reasons tomorrow. Let's just first get the
facts down. אבא שאול אומר מיטיב ואחר כך מקטיר. Abba Shaul omer
meitiv veachar kach maktir. אבא שאול Abba Shaul said: No, I think
that you are, that
you fully do the lighting, right, and then you do the קטורת.
ketoret.
Right, which is this, which is you fully do the lighting so
you're gonna interrupt it, you're gonna interrupt it with דם dam and
then the קטורת ketoret comes after, okay? So is that clear? The
first position said do some of the קטורת ketoret before you're finished
with the מנורה. menorah. There has to be קטורת ketoret and then
מנורה. menorah. So that's the first way we said that it works
with the משניות mishnayos that the קטורת ketoret comes in between. Do
the קטורת ketoret and then finish the מנורה. menorah. אבא שאול Abba
Shaul goes: No, no, no, finish the מנורה menorah fully and then
do the קטורת. ketoret. So then what are you going to interrupt
it with? According to him, you'll interrupt it with the דם. dam.
Okay, אבא שאול אומר מיטיב ואחר כך מקטיר. Abba Shaul omer meitiv
veachar kach maktir. First fully do the מנורה menorah and then do
the קטורת. ketoret. מאי טעמא דאבא שאול? mai taama d'Abba Shaul? Finally
let's get to some reasoning. What's his reasoning to say that the
קטורת ketoret comes after the מנורה menorah is finished? Well, it's a
פסוק, דכתיב: בבקר בבקר בהטיבו את הנרות יקטירנה. baboker baboker beheitivo es
haneros yaktirena. First do the נרות neros and then it says and
then you burn the incense. So that's why finish all of it
and then burn the incense. ורבנן מאי טעמא רחמנא. verabbanan mai taama
rachmana. ורבנן, verabbanan, and the Rabbis would say, מאי קאמר רחמנא? mai
kaamar rachmana? What does what does the Torah saying? בעידן הטבה תהא
הקטרת קטורת. be'idan hatava tehei haktarat ketoret. It's saying it doesn't mean
you finish all of the lighting and then you burn the קטורת.
ketoret. It means during the period of the lighting you do the
קטורת, ketoret, which actually means do the קטורת. ketoret. In the middle
of the lighting, right? בבוקר בבוקר בהטיבו
את הנרות יקטירנה baboker baboker behetivo et hanerot yakteirenah
during the period of בהטיבו את הנרות יקטירנה behetivo et hanerot yakteirenah
so you do it in the middle. You don't do it after.
You do it during. Okay, so basically what we have here is
that the rabbis say the קטורת k'tores בהטיבו את הנרות יקטירנה behetivo
et hanerot yakteirenah the קטורת k'tores takes place in the middle to
between, you know, between the two parts of the מנורה. menorah. And
that explains the משניות mishnayos that sometimes have the מנורה menorah before
and sometimes after. It has the קטורת k'tores in the middle. אביי
Abaye who says the דם dam is in the middle is following
אבא שאול. Abba Shaul. אבא שאול Abba Shaul says בהטיבו את הנרות
behetivo et hanerot first you finish the נרות nerot and then יקטירנה
yakteirenah and then the קטורת. k'tores. If it's going to be divided,
it's going to be divided by the דם. dam. Okay, so we'll
continue with that debate tomorrow and finally start getting into some of
the reasons behind that.